<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A broken heart, or The grand sacrifice. As it was laid out in a sermon preached at St. Maries in Beverley, in the East-riding of the county of Yorke, upon the monthly fast-day in Christmas-weeke, being Decemb. 28. 1642. By John Shawe, pastor of the church at Rotherham in the same county.</title>
            <author>Shawe, John, 1608-1672.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 81 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93050</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3027</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E95_13</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12113</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859212</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859212</idno>
            <idno type="VID">111281</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93050)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 111281)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 17:E95[13])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A broken heart, or The grand sacrifice. As it was laid out in a sermon preached at St. Maries in Beverley, in the East-riding of the county of Yorke, upon the monthly fast-day in Christmas-weeke, being Decemb. 28. 1642. By John Shawe, pastor of the church at Rotherham in the same county.</title>
                  <author>Shawe, John, 1608-1672.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>in the yeare 1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: The broken heart, or grand sacrifice.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill. 10".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms LI, 16-17 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:111281:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A BROKEN HEART, OR THE GRAND SACRIFICE. AS IT WAS LAID OVT IN A SERMON PREACHED AT St. MARIES in Beverley, in the Eaſt-riding of the County of <hi>Yorke,</hi> upon the monthly Faſt-day in Chriſtmas-weeke, being <hi>Decemb.</hi> 28. 1642.</p>
            <p>By JOHN SHAWE, Paſtor of the Church at <hi>Rotherham</hi> in the ſame County.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>ISAIAH 57. 15. </bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>For thus ſaith the high and loſty One; that inhabiteth eternity, whoſe name is holy, I dwell in the high and holy place, with him alſo that is of a contrite and humble ſpirit, to revive the ſpirit of the humble, and to revive the heart of the contrite ones.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>ISAIAH 66. 2. </bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>But to this man will I looke, even to him that is poore and of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite ſpirit, and trembleth at my Word.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed at London in the yeare 1643.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:111281:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT VVorſhipful M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> THOMAS RAYKES, Major of the ſtrong and populous Towne of <hi>Kingston</hi> upon <hi>Hull,</hi> and all the Aldermen thereof, to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Richard Wood,</hi> Sheriffe, and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Iames Lupton,</hi> and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>William Raykes,</hi> Chamberlaines of the ſame famous Corporation, and to all the reſt both of the high and low Church Pariſhes: <hi>I. S.</hi> wiſheth truth <hi>add peace here, life and glory after by Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Worſhipfull and much honoured Sirs,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE eagerneſſe and importunitie of thoſe amongſt you whom it moſt concerned, ſo preſſingly inviting me to come over to you for the ſervice of your Faith, the worke of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery, when dangers and troubles ſhould ariſe in mine owne Hemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phere, together with your unanimous and free choyce of mee for that work, during the continuance of ſuch ſtormes, have moved mee to hazard my ſelfe on the publique cenſure, that I may hereby acknowledge your kind reſpect, and returne you deſerved thankes. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly when ſtormes aroſe at home, and the provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God opened a doore; at your requeſt I came over to you, why I ſtaid not with you, (but remain here at B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>verl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, ſix miles from you, and forty miles from the ſmoake of mine own cabbin) you well know: I have
<pb facs="tcp:111281:2"/> not now to accuſe any, or Magiſtrate, or Miniſter, or people; this only I am moſt confident of, that the great God who now knowes, and ere long will reveale and judge the ſecrets of all then, will manifeſt that in this bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe I had (and I verily ſo think of you) neither inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, nor endevour, but ſuch as are agreeable to Gods Word, and the Parliaments order: I heartily wiſh that the ſucc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe of this buſineſſe may further (that which in the Sermon I drive at) both in you and me, <hi>Broken hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedneſſe</hi> and contrition of ſpirit: my prayers are, that the publique curſes wiſhed may never fall on you; but that the bleſſings of peace may ever flouriſh within your gates, both peace within you, peace of conſcience, by framing your converſation to Gods Word; and peace above you peace with God, through the Reconciler Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt; and peace without you, peace with men, which is alwayes good and pleaſant, eſpecially now, and chiefly in your Towne, when it is attendant to truth and holineſſe. The Lord ever keep you from that evill ſpirit of diſſention, <hi>Judg.</hi> 9. 23. and grant that thoſe eſpecially who ought moſt to be men of peace, may never for their own <note n="a" place="margin">Num. 11. 29 <hi>otherwiſe affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted were Iohn Baptist,</hi> John 3. 29, 30. <hi>and Paul,</hi> Phil. 1. 18.</note> honour, gaine, or private ends, make any breach in the walls of Jeruſalem. I had rather with <hi>Jonah</hi> be eaſt into the Sea, then wilfully make publique rents in Chriſts ſeamleſſe Coat. My intreaty to you is, not to truſt in any outward ſtrength or fortifications, leſt ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>confidence be your ruine, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30 3. <hi>Jer.</hi> 17. 5, 6. you ſee in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 22. verl. 8 9, 10, 11. that <hi>Judah</hi> got Armes and ſouldiers, made ditches, trenches, bulwarks, &amp;c. But heare what God ſaith, verſ. 12, 13, 14. That without <hi>Heart-breaking</hi> and <hi>humiliation,</hi> all theſe could not ſave them: You know what was ſaid to <hi>Phocas,</hi> If you build your walls to heaven, yet if ſinger in, it will ruine them all: Theſe fortifications cannot keep out the worſt enemies, as firſt ſin, ſecond Gods wrath, third ſickneſſe, fourth death, fifth devils, ſixth burning conſcience now, ſeventh hell, &amp;c. Labour therefore, I pray you, for true
<pb facs="tcp:111281:3"/> repetance, that is the way to make a Kingdome or Towne ſtand, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11. 21, 23. had Sodome and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrah repented, they had ſtood till this day. How did this prolong Nineveh? <hi>Jonahs</hi> firſt words to Nineveh implyed this, and holy <hi>Bradfords</hi> laſt words at the ſtake expreſſed it, <hi>viz.</hi> Repent, O England, repent, repent! Of al enemies and treacheries take heed of that cheating theefe, and devilliſh traytor, raigning ſinne: that would both diſcourage and ruine you. I remember a ſweet and experimentall paſſage of the old Earle of Eſſex (Father to his Excellencie that now is in the Field) which was preached at <hi>Pauls</hi> Croſſe the Lords day next after his death; When I have gone out in a morning (ſaid he) and found ſome guilt lye on my conſcience, no man was more cowardly then I; but when I went to prayer in a morning, and found a cleare conſcience and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of peace with God, I durſt have encountred an armie of men, as bold as a Lion. Such like expreſſion I find of that Leiceſter-ſhire Martyr, old Father <hi>Latimer.</hi> Secondly, practiſe that which was the cloſe of many of the Martyrs Letters, Pray, pray, pray. When <hi>Jacob</hi> ſtood like a Vertue betwixt two vices: on one hand, had had <hi>Laban,</hi> and now <hi>Eſau</hi> and his crew on the other; <hi>Jacob</hi> goes over the brooke alone, and wreſtles with God; and though the longer he ſtrove, the weaker, the lamer he grew, yet holds out (like <hi>Moſes</hi> on the Mount) till the day, til he got a bleſſing, and <hi>Eſau's</hi> killing is tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to kiſſing, <hi>Gen.</hi> 32. 24. &amp; 33. 4. See how prayer helps and ſaves in the worſt times, <hi>Joel</hi> 2. 31, 32. I remember what I have read of <hi>Luther,</hi> that he prayed five houres a day <hi>(eaſque ſtudio optiſſimas)</hi> and that when he dyed, the bords of his cloſet, where he uſed to pray, were found rotten with tears that fell from his eyes in prayer. Thirdly, labour to beleeve, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20. 20. by faith get into thoſe chambers of protection, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26. 20. the cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Gods attributes, of his decrees, of his promiſes, of his ſpeciall providence, principally the rocke Jeſus <note place="margin">Cant. 2. 14.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:111281:3"/> Chriſt. I remember another paſſage of <hi>Luther,</hi> when they told him of the malice, power, and preparation that the Pope and his complices had againſt him; Come, come (ſaid he) let us ſing the 46. Pſalme, and let them doe the worſt they can: O but (ſaid ſome) they have made a decree againſt you at Norinberge; Oh! (ſaid he) but there is another decree in heaven, and that muſt ſtand; I (ſaid he) have hitherto kept out Pope, Spaine, and the Devil, by prayer; and when I am gone, they that would keep him out muſt uſe the ſame way. But the porch growes great; give me leave to preſent theſe ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt meditations (ſuch as they are) to your hands, eyes, and hearts; and to ſhelter them (that I ſay not my ſelf) under all your Patronage: The bleſſing of him that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in the Buſh go with them, and be on you; who ſhall ever have the ferventeſt prayers, heartieſt thanks, and true affections of him who is,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>At your command in and for the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of my Maſter Chriſts JOHN SHAWE.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Beverley,</hi>
                  <date>Jan. 5. 1642.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:111281:4"/>
            <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER, ESPECIALLY TO THE INHA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BITANTS WITHIN THE TOWNE and Pariſh of <hi>Rotherham;</hi> and others, to whom the Author hath had par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular relation.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian and courteous Reader:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F you aske mee why, firſt this Sermon, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly at this time, thirdly in ſuch a plaine dreſſe, homely garbe, and phraſe, comes now to ſtand in white ſheetes before the publique view; take my anſwer to each in a word.</p>
            <p>To the firſt, thus, When this Sermon was preached in this place (where by the providence of God I am caſt at preſent) the watery eyes, attentive eares, and tongues of many, moſt begged this. Secondly, among other notes (whether ſafe or loſt I well know not) theſe on the ſudden I thought not unſutable to the preſent times.</p>
            <p>To the ſecond, thus, I being now abſent from home, found ſome (though but little) time, to write over theſe my thoughts: Againe, I thought hereby ſomewhat to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence my neceſſitated abſence from mine owne people this way.</p>
            <p>To the third, thus, I was at the preaching hereof forty miles abſent from my bookes, and ſuddenly called to this worke, and had time only once to write theſe notes over,
<pb facs="tcp:111281:4"/> and that in the time of no ſmall diſtractions, and was wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to print it as it was preached, as neere as conveniently I could (elſe I could not well have called it the ſame Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon) moreover, I thought the plaineſt phraſe, without all curious dreſſe, did beſt become theſe times, and the day and occaſion of this Sermon. God grant I may do that by printing, and you by reading, which may keep us both from ſinning, and further us in the way of heart-breaking. If thou either bring a broken heart to the reading of thoſe notes, or hereby doeſt got one, their plaineneſſe will downe the better: if neither, I much regard not thy cenſure. How-ever, if thy palate be too curious, I ſhall commend the peruſall of them to others, in whom I conceive my ſelf to have ſome more intereſt, as being my ſpeciall friends, at <note n="“" place="margin">
                  <hi>As</hi> Cutthorp, Somerſall, &amp;c.</note> Brampton in Derby-ſhire, at Chimloigh in <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>As</hi> Heanton, Newplace, Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Colla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on, Raſhl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, and M. <hi>Ro. Sk. &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> Devon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire; Alhallowes on the pavement in Yorke; Bradfield, and <note n="b" place="margin">To ſome who in theſe times have fled hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for refuge, as the Lady <hi>M.</hi> who hath been already plunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in York of a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 1000. p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unds, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s yet out above 700 <hi>Ald V.</hi> and divers others inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants alſo.</note> Beverley, and principally my tenderly affected ſtock at Rotherham in Yorkſhire; let (oh let) me prevaile with all you to ſet after heaven with a godly violence, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11. 12. <hi>Feare not the preſent diſtempers, combuſtions, rubs, and troubles;</hi> it is one ſign Antichriſt is going down, he rageth ſo ſore, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. 12. no violent thing is perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, when one works exceeding hard, we ſay he will get done quickly; <hi>dolor ſi gravis, brevis;</hi> it is but <hi>nub. cula cito tranſitura.</hi> Cheare up and courage (beloved) as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> did in the worſt times; when not onely friends and goods, but wives and al gone, yet God was not gone, <hi>1 Sam.</hi> 30. 6. this made him, and thoſe bleſſed worthies to take joyfully the plundering of their goods, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 34. heaven will pay for all ere long; know that no affliction or croſſe comes on us, till there be great need of it for us, <hi>1 Pet. 1. 6.</hi> comes not without an everlaſting knowledge and decree of God before time, <hi>Act. 4. 28. Epheſ. 1. 5.</hi> and is ordered by Gods all-wiſe diſpoſing providence in time, not onely God takes care of things in heaven, but on earth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 113. 6. not only of men on earth, but beaſts, yea birds, yea little birds, yea poore ſparrowes, whereof two are ſold for one
<pb facs="tcp:111281:5"/> 
               <hi>farthing,</hi> Matth. 10. 29. <hi>and five for two farthings,</hi> Luk, 12. 6. <hi>yea theſe poore birds move not; hop not from bough to bough</hi> (ibid.) <hi>without Gods providence; may, takes not care only of mans eſſentiall or internall parts, but of his very haires which are but excrements,</hi> Matth. 10. 30. <hi>if a haire cannot fal from our heads without Gods providence, much leſſe our heads from our ſhoulders; nor ſhall any of these croſſes last longer then ſerves for our profit,</hi> Hebr. 12. 10. My times are in thy hands <hi>(not in mans, or my enemies)</hi> O Lord, <hi>ſaid</hi> David, <hi>Pſal. 31. 15. When the ſore is healed, the plaſter will fall off, when the enemies have puſhed us nigher heaven, God will then knock, off the horns,</hi> Zach. 1. 20, 21. <hi>burne the rod,</hi> Iſa. 10. 5. <hi>What can ſword or ſtaffe do without an hand to guide it? The end and iſſue will be happie,</hi> Iſa. 3. 9. <hi>only be we mourners, get Chriſts marke,</hi> Ezek. 9. 4. <hi>He that hath delivered us from the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 28.</note> and the Beare, will deliver us from this Philiſtine. Let us pray, heare, reade, &amp;c. but let all come from broken hearts; lap up all in contrition of ſpirit. T though we have ſought long, and ſtill things ſeeme to go worſe and worſe; yet ſee how</hi> Jacob <hi>at length (not at first) prevailed with the Angel.</hi> Moſes <hi>on the Mount;</hi> Exod. 17. <hi>the importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate widow with the judge,</hi> Luk. 18. 5. <hi>and 11. 8. After the <note place="margin">Luke 11. 8.</note> ſharpeſt ſtorme comes the ſweeteſt ſunſhine: God can make the valley of Achor for a dore of hope,</hi> Hoſ. 2. 15. <hi>Let me beg of every Chriſtian Reader a prayer and a teare: I have ſaid; let us both practiſe, and God give a bleſſing. Amen, and Amen:</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>So prayes I. S.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Jan. 6. 1642.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:111281:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>PSALME 51. <hi>ver. 16, 17.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>For thou deſtreſt not Sacrifice, elſe would I give it: thou delighteſt not in burnt Offerings, 17. The Sacrifices of God are a broken ſpirit: a broken and a contrite heart, O God, thou wilt not deſpiſe.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>onder not (Right worſhipfull and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved) <note place="margin">* A Chriſtmas as poore people ſay againſt a good time.</note> that theſe times (by the voyce of the multitude call'd good or the beſt times, but by the practice of the moſt, made the worſt times; wherein many uſe Chriſt worſe then helliſh <hi>Iudas,</hi> or deviliſh <hi>Pilate;</hi> they let him live till hee was above thirty three yeares old; but many uſe him like a Babyloniſh brat, daſhing out his braines as ſoone as he is borne) won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der not I ſay that theſe times, too commonly made times of feaſting and merriment, are now become times of faſting and mourning; (yea, not the ſixth or ſeventh <hi>(as Zach 7.)</hi> but the twelvemonth faſt) our Saviour tels that
<q>when he Bridegroom ſhould be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kne away, then ſhould they faſt in thoſe dayes;</q> Now
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:111281:6"/> when our Bridegroome Chriſt ſeemes to remove from the Temple, from the Cherub from the thr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſhold, to the Mountaine <hi>(Ezek.</hi> 9. &amp; 10. &amp; 11.) When our God ſeems to be removed from our Land (heretofore the glory of Lands, the fortunate Iland) by reaſon of our ſinues, witneſſe our wars and divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions from his ordinances; witneſſe that want of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer efficacy, and power: from his peoples feeling, witneſſe their feares and troubles: and when his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Majeſty alſo is removed ſo far (alas too far) from his great councell; no wonder if we faſt in theſe dayes; I have read, in our Chronicles, though now I cannot on the ſudden tell where, (being far removed from my ſtudy, Bookes and papers) that heretofore there was in <hi>England</hi> a Chriſtmas kept, called the ſilent and dumbe Chriſtmas; becauſe of a great af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction of God upon this Land, the people were ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent from their wonted mirth and ſports; ſure if e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver this Land had cauſe, now much more, to keepe a ſilent and dumbe Chriſtmaſſe; It was a ſavory paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of <hi>Vriah, 2. Sam.</hi> 11. 11. When the Arke and <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Iudab</hi> abide in Tents; and my Lord <hi>Ioab,</hi> and the ſervants of my Lord encampe in the Fields, ſhall I then, &amp;c. Take my lawfull liberty? and <hi>David</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, If I forget <hi>Ierusalem</hi> in my mirth, &amp;c. Faſting and Prayer if rightly performed have a great preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency with the great God; a wreſtling power, and binding power, <hi>Ex.</hi> 32. A commanding power, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45. 11. See in old Teſtament, <hi>Iudg</hi> 20. There was a ſcareful civill War in the ſame Land, amongſt Gods people of the ſame religion (by profeſſion); the cauſe was, <hi>Benjamin</hi> would not ſuffer malignant delinquent
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:111281:6"/> parties to come to condigne puniſhment. The eleven Tribes ſend firſt to know the truth whether there was ſuch a fact done or no, its proved <hi>ver.</hi> 3, 4, 5. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, they offer faire termes of peace to their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, only let the delinquents be puniſhed <hi>vers.</hi> 12. 13. Thirdly, when theſe faire proffers were rejected, then reſolve they to goe and fight with their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, ſome of them to fight, and others to be ſut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers for the Army <hi>Vers.</hi> 9. 10. And forth they goe. 400000 of <hi>Israel</hi> againſt 26000 of <hi>Benjamin;</hi> ſo that the people of <hi>Isarel</hi> had far more men, a far better cauſe, and a good warrant (the Command of God himſelfe <hi>(Vers.</hi> 18. 23.) Yet loſt they in two Battells far more men then the enemy had in all, even 40000 <hi>Vers.</hi> 21, 25. But when they went to faſting and prayer (which before they omitted) <hi>Vers.</hi> 26. Then they beate downe all before them; till themſelves fell a weeping for the loſſe of a Tribe <hi>Iudg.</hi> 21. 23. <note place="margin">Mat. 17. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1.</note> So in New Teſtament ſome devills are not caſt out by Prayer only, and other good meanes, but by faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Prayer. See how faſting turned quite about the heart of the greateſt King in the World, to hate malignants and to affect Gods Church, though a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his owne decree and purpoſe; one night a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all the reſt <hi>Abaſhnerus</hi> could notſleepe, he calls not for company, but a booke; no booke, but booke of Chronicles would ſerve; no page in that wherein <hi>Mordecaies</hi> good fact was mentioned, <hi>Est.</hi> 6. But ſee how <hi>Eſther</hi> firſt prevailed with God, <hi>Cap.</hi> 4. 16, 17. So when a Kingdome was upon the knee, within forty dayes of giving up the Ghoſt; yet Faſting and Prayer was one helpe to bring
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:111281:7"/> all ſafe back againe, <hi>Ionah</hi> 3. 5, 6, 7, 8. I might be large this way, I onely ſhew how needfull this worke is even now. Onely (that we may doe it aright) know its not abſtaining from meate and drinke for a day (ſo far as our bodily health and infirmities will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit) and from workes of our calling, ſports, and coſtly apparell (ſo indeed ſackcloth and aſhes might better become us this day, if it were the cuſtome of <note place="margin">Iſa. 58. 5, 6, 7. Faſt day ſhould be ſpent as a Sabbath, Lev. 23. 28. Iſa. 58. 13.</note> our Country, then coſty apparell <hi>Ionah</hi> 3. 5.) all this is but the outward, the leaſt part; but the main work of a faſt ſtands in three things, 1. Heart-breaking humiliation, called a day to afflict a mans ſoule in, <hi>Levit.</hi> 23. 27. Soule-pricking ſorrow. Secondly, to endeavor after, and beg reconciliation and peace with God; things can never goe well.) hence its cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a day of attonement. <hi>Levit.</hi> 23. 27. Thirdly, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation to amend in Perſons, Families, Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, Kingdomes, what is amiſſe, ſo far as in us lies; elſe let <hi>Ioſhua</hi> and Elders weep, rent their cloths, and faſt, it will not do, till curſed perſons and curſed things be removed <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 7. 6, 7, 10, 11. <hi>Iſa,</hi> 58.
<note place="margin">Neh. 9. 38. &amp; 10. 28, 29.</note> 5, 6. Faſts uſed therefore to be cloſed up with a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant; <hi>Neh.</hi> 9. 38. Now that we may performe this inward and maine part of a holy Faſt this day, I have graſped up ſome few thoughts (ſuch as in this want of Bookes, in this diſtracted condition I can,) which may helpe us in this heart-breaking, and ſoule-reforming worke; a thing alwayes needfull, but for the ſalving of diſtreſſed <hi>Ireland,</hi> and cement<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſtracted <hi>England,</hi> a very None ſuch; out of, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.</p>
            <p>This is <hi>Davids</hi> maine penitentiall <hi>Pſalme,</hi> which <note place="margin">Pſal. 51.</note>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:111281:7"/> after he had ſo fouly ſinned with <hi>Bathſheba,</hi> beene guilty of the murder of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah</hi> made his ſervants ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, &amp;c. And, Secondly, after almoſt a whole <note place="margin">See the ſtory of it in, 2 Sam. 11. 12.</note> yeares lying in this ſinne, <hi>Nathan</hi> had both covertly and openly reproved him, and Thirdly, God had ſmitten his Conſcience, and given him true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, when he penned this Pſalm.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Wherein he heartily and exemplarily expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <note place="margin">Pſalme hath two parts, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in ver. 18. &amp; concerning the Church till end.</note> his Repentance in three things. 1. Confeſſion and that, Firſt. Of his ſinnes in generall, how many and hainous they were, <hi>Verſ</hi> 1, 2, 3. Secondly, of his particular ſinnes he was in eſpeciall guilty of <hi>Ver.</hi> 14. Thirdly, of the fountaine, ſpring, and roote of all this miſchife, <hi>Ver.</hi> 5.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Petition, and that of three things, (in all the World moſt neceſſary,) Firſt, Juſtification or free pardon of ſinnes, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 1. 2. Secondly, of Sanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or healing and renewing grace, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 10, &amp;c. Thirdly, of aſſurance, (which is the wel-being of the ſoule) <hi>Verſ.</hi> 8. 12.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Reſolution, what <hi>David</hi> would doe upon this, <hi>Viz.</hi> Serve and praiſe God better, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 15. The manner how <hi>David</hi> would hereafter praiſe God is ſet out in my Text two wayes, 1. Negatively not with Sacrifices nor burnt Offerings, 2. Affirmatively, but with a broken and contrite heart: for the firſt, why he would not doe it with Sacrifices, &amp;c. Hee gives two reaſons, 1. <hi>A priori</hi> God never deſired them aforehand, 2. God never delighted in them afterward.</p>
            <p>For the ſecond, why hee would ſerve God with a broken heart, &amp;c. He implies in theſe words three
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:111281:8"/> reaſons, 1. A broken heart is Sacrifices in the plurall number, <hi>i. e.</hi> Wheras there were five ſorts of Sacrifices in the old law, <hi>viz</hi> Burnt-offering, Meate-offering, Peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>offering, Sin-offering and Treſpaſſe-offering, this bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken heart is <hi>inſtar omnium,</hi> as good, nay better then all. 2, Sacrifices of God:] <hi>i. e.</hi> The beſt and eminenteſt kind of Sacrifices, (as Mountaine of God, Word of God, people of God, are the eminenteſt.) 3. Such as God will not deſpiſe, <hi>i. e.</hi> Highly prize and value, as 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5. 20. Deſpiſe not, <hi>i. e.</hi> Highly prize pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſing.</p>
            <p>There remaines now one maine rubb, or materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Objection in the way to be removed, and then I ſhall poſt apace, and caſe you with what haſt I may.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> How can it be ſaid that God required not neither delighted in ſacrifices? &amp;c. Seeing in the book of <hi>Leviticus,</hi> in all ceremoniall Law, God comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them, his people in the old Teſtament dayly offered them, and God was well pleaſed with, and accepted of them, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 4. <hi>Gen.</hi> 8. 20. 21. Nay in the next Verſe but one of this, <hi>Pſal. David,</hi> promiſeth them <hi>verſe</hi> 19.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> To this our Divines doe (as I conceive truly and fully) give anſwer in two points. Firſt, God never required Sacrifices comparatively: <hi>i. e.</hi> In com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of a broken heart its nothing, its not to be compared with it, thus <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6. 6. Mercy and not Sacrifice, <hi>i. e.</hi> More, or rather then Sacrifice, thus <hi>Ioel:</hi> 2. 13. <hi>Rend your hearts and not your garments.</hi> i. e. <hi>Rather.</hi> Secondly, God never required them abſtractly &amp; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from a broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heart; the beſt Sacrifices without
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:111281:8"/> a broken heart God never delighted in: thus <hi>Iſai.</hi> 1. 11, 12, 13. Who required your Burnt Offerings, Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Sabbaths, new Moones, <hi>id eſt,</hi> God never requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red or delighted in the beſt of theſe, joyned with li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in their ſins, verſ. 16. and ſevered from a broken heart; thus concerning faſting, ſee <hi>Iſai.</hi> 58. 4, 5.</p>
            <p>I will ſlaſh our Text no longer, as ſome doe their garments, till more gay and leſſe warme, <hi>idem vitii habet nimia, as nulla diviſio,</hi> this is not a day of curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous dividing Texts, much leſſe Kingdomes, but hearts only; this ſad day and time ſpeaks, no curious toyes, but plaine dealing; expect not much from me (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved) that can performe but little at beſt, eſpecially on this ſuddaine, chiefly now, being from books and meanes, thus torne, diſtracted and divided.</p>
            <p>Obſerve onely (after our plaine homeſpun Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey manner) two plain truths from theſe two verſes, 1. from the 16. verſ.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſer.</hi> That all the beſt outward dutyes and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices (ſuch as God in his word requires) if performed without a broken and contrite heart are no way de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightſome but diſpleaſing to God. See for this <hi>Iſai.</hi> 1. 11, 12, 13, 14. &amp; 66. 2, 3.</p>
            <p>The Scripture mentions, that the beſt duties and ſervices done without a broken heart, God abhors the dutyes, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. 13. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66. 18. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66. 2, 3. as if it had not been done, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 28, 29.</p>
            <p>2 Abhors the perſon or doer of ſuch ſervices, cals them dogs dirt, chaffe, &amp;c. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 5. God was not pleaſed with ſuch perſons; and the <hi>Phariſee</hi> for all his faſting (more then ordinary,) and paying, and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, went away not juſtified, <hi>Luk.</hi> 18. 12, 13, 14.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:111281:9"/>
            <p>3 Will damne them hereafter not withſtanding all their duties, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7. 21. <hi>Luk.</hi> 13. 27. All theſe can no more hinder the fire of Gods wrath, from deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Kingdomes or perſons, then a wiſpe of dry ſtraw can ſtop fire from entring in at a gap. <hi>Zach.</hi> 7. And not onely Scripture, but all reaſon ſpeakes this truth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 1. From the words of text, becauſe God ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver required them; Prayer, hearing, keeping Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths, receiving Sacraments God indeed requires and enjoynes (ſo did he Sacrifices) but Prayer, hearing, receiving, &amp;c. without a broken heart, ſuch God never required; from the firſt of <hi>Geneſis</hi> to the laſt of <hi>Revelation,</hi> no one place ever required ſuch, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 58. 5. <hi>Ier.</hi> 7. 22, 23. God never ſpake one word of ſuch.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 2. Becauſe ſuch empty ſervices <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 10. 1. as are without this brokenneſſe; are in Scripture cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, duties and no duties, ſervices and no ſervices (as is ſaid in the Riddle) 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 17. in verſ. 33. Text ſaith, thoſe mongrel <hi>Samaritans</hi> feared God. But next verſe it ſaith, they feared not God, ſo 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 28. 6. Its ſaid that <hi>Saul</hi> enquired of the Lord, yet 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 10. 14. <hi>Saul</hi> enquired not of the Lord, ſo in 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. 23, 24. with 3. 13. Thus ancients expound thoſe places, where its ſaid that the <hi>Jewes</hi> ſought not God, faſted not, were not circumciſed, as <hi>Jer.</hi> 9. 25, 26. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 3. Becauſe ſuch ſervices are but bodily exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 8. Now of your deareſt Wife, Child, &amp;c. What do you care for the preſence of their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy (though never ſo beautifull and pleaſant former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) if it want a heart, a ſoul? no, you ſay with <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:111281:9"/> let me bury my dead out of my ſight; no more doth God care for carcaſſes, and rotten outſides of duties, ſuch Circumciſion bodily only, is nothing, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 25, 26. <hi>Ier.</hi> 9. 25, 26.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 4. When men forme glorious outward ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces without broken hearts, they pride themſelves in, and reſt on them; now reſting upon duties, upon the <hi>opus operatum,</hi> or worke done, is one kind of ſpiritual Idolatry; I know no more reaſon that a man ſhould worſhip the Croſſe, becauſe Chriſt ſuffered on it; then that a man ſhould worſhip the Gibbet or Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes becauſe his father or brother ſuffered thereon: The Croſſe was no piece of our redemption; I know no more reaſon why I ſhould worſhip an Image (though never ſo gloriouſly guilded,) then that I ſhould worſhip a dog, or graſſe, that is the workman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of man; theſe of Gods hands, and ſo more emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent; and yet I know no more reaſon to reſt on du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties then either of the former.</p>
            <p>Is there no kinde of Idolatrie but worſhipping ſtocks, and ſtones? yes <hi>Ezek.</hi> 14. 7. witneſſe ſecond Commandement reſting on Temple of the Lord, Temple of the Lord; God can abide nothing worſe <note place="margin">Ier. 7. 4.</note> then pride in their performances, this honey in their Sacrifices; when they come with handfulls to God; ſee <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. 21. 23. <hi>Luk.</hi> 13. 27, 28. <hi>Phariſees</hi> did per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme abundance of duties, hecatombes of Sacrifices <note place="margin">Matth. 6. 2. 5. 7.</note> ſome ſay they prayed eight houres a day, and yet ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept our righteouſneſſe go beyond theirs, no heaven <hi>Matt.</hi> 5. 20.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 5. Breaking of the heart is the end of Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, therefore better then they; what are they with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:111281:10"/> it? Sacrifices not onely (though mainly) typed out that true propitiatory Sacrifice, The <hi>Lambe</hi> of God that takes away ſins of world, but alſo ſhadow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out the cutting aſunder, and breaking of the heart of him that brought it; renting of cloths, noted ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of heart.</p>
            <p>I ſee more Corne under my hand, then I can threſh out ſpeedily, and yet your extraordinary occaſions <note n="*" place="margin">Mr. Major ſent us word that he had e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecial com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand about the Souldiers that day.</note> this day cauſe me cut ſhort my diſtracted thoughts; and therefore becauſe I would mainly inſiſt on the ſecond point, I muſt adjourne the other reaſons and uſes of this point, and remaine your debter till ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time, only mentioning one or two of the heads, and that but like Gideons Souldiers, lap and away.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſe</hi> 1. Its no ſigne then of the true Religion to have an outward glorious pompous outſide; no, if it want a broken heart, its but vaine oblations, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. 13. but taking Gods name in vaine. <hi>Satan</hi> may ſtill dwell in the heart, for all <hi>Iudaſes</hi> devotion, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 13. 27. And himſelfe be a devill, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6. 70. Wee may for all them neither truly draw nigh to God, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15. 8. Nor he to us, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1. 27, 28, 29. Indeed was it not ſo, I would confeſſe that bloodſucking Monſter of <hi>Rome</hi> (that kills the bodies, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. 15. and ſells ſoules of men, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18. 13.) To carry away the Bell from all Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, for guilded Pictures, Veſtments, Tapers, Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, cringings, bowings, Crucifixes, Altars, Muſicke, &amp;c. Long Prayers, ſtrange geſtures, (to make ſport for children) and I heare them brag of theſe; Alas who required theſe; and had they bin good, (as they are not) yet one broken heart, or one poore ſervants Prayer with a broken heart is worth 10000. of them.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:111281:10"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſe</hi> 2. Would have told us, that in old Teſtament as well as new, God required ſpiritual ſervice, elſe cringing and laying hand on head of Sacrifice, would not ſerve, without ſlaying ſinne, and broken hearts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſe</hi> 3. Thoſe may be dub'd for fooles then, that ground their ſalvation, and boaſt upon their good duties without brokeneſſe and humbleneſſe of ſpirit: alas <hi>Ahab</hi> repeated, <hi>Simon Magus</hi> believed, <hi>Herod</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, <hi>Iudas</hi> preached, many wrought miracles, <hi>Matt.</hi> 7. <hi>Phariſees faſted, gave Almes, and prayed. Matt.</hi> 6. yet loſt both themſelves and their labour, there are ſource things men count eminent, and much reſt on.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Naturall abilities of body and minde, yet for all <hi>Achitophels</hi> wit, <hi>Goliahs</hi> ſtrength, <hi>Abſolons</hi> beauty, <hi>Balams</hi> ſubtilty, may periſh eternally.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Artificiall Endowments: Yet <hi>Demetrius</hi> for all his art, <hi>Iulian</hi> for all his learning may periſh, &amp;c. A thouſand others have had good parts and gifts this way, good head-pieces, but bad heart-pieces, like a Toade with a Pearle in her head, but poyſonous body.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Glorious duties: yet all they, <hi>Matt.</hi> 6. praying, hearing, <hi>Matt.</hi> 7. 21, 22. <hi>Luk.</hi> 13. 27 Cry, it is not in me; are they Gods to ſave? they are but Bridges to lead us to Chriſt, 4. glittering graces, ſuch as five fooliſh <hi>Virgins</hi> had. <hi>Ahabs</hi> repentance; <hi>Magus's</hi> faith, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> 4. This would tell us alſo of the ſtraite gate to life and broad way to hell; not onely heatheniſh <hi>Pagans,</hi> Secondly, idolatrous Chriſtians (if ſo I may terme ſo foule a thing with ſo faire a name,) Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, prophane vitious Proteſtants, but Fourthly, fooliſh
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:111281:11"/> virgios that have lamps without true Oyle, <hi>Math.</hi> 25. 3. Want the Oyle typed out, <hi>Exod.</hi> 30. 23, 24. Made of the dropping myrre of true Repentance; the ſtrong Cinamon of a lively faith, the large ſpreading Caſſis of univerſall obedience, a ſweet ſmelling <hi>Calamus</hi> (or Oyle Olive) of love. I ſay even the beſt of theſe without broken hearts cannot pleaſe God, therefore many periſh, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſe.</hi> 5. Sheves a golden path between two Rocks, neither leave the duties undone, nor yet carnally ſhuffle them over, but doe them, 1. From a right prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, a broken ſpirit, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1. 25 4. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4. 23. The want of this ſpoild <hi>Jehues</hi> zeale, 2 <hi>Ki</hi> 10. 31. <hi>Iudas</hi> his piety, <hi>Iewes</hi> devotion, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15. 8. &amp; 23. 28. Like watches, clocks, jacks, ran apace, <hi>(are Automata)</hi> but no life within. 2. For a right end, not for our ſelves, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 0 1. Our praiſe as Phariſees to be ſeene of men, or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, as <hi>Iudas</hi> for bag; or feare of puniſhment onely as <hi>Iewes Zach.</hi> 7. 5, 6. For knavery, to cover and colour it. <hi>Pro.</hi> 7. 14, 15. But for Gods glory, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 31. 3ly. By a right rule, according to Gods Word, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8. 5. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 19. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 14. They erre therefore that doe duties from a wrong principle, Lamps without Oyle: a wrong end, as <hi>Iehu</hi> for a Kingdome: by a wrong rule <hi>Iſa</hi> 58. 5. Outwardly without heart, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15. 8. When reſt upon them, the Temple of the Lord, Temple of the Lord: when ſtill live in their ſins, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. 16. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 66. 18.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſe.</hi> 6. Try whether we are like to doe poore <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> diſtreſſed <hi>England</hi> any good this day, we have now kept faſts theſe 12. Months, but is it with broken hearts, <hi>Zach.</hi> 7. 5. 6. Or only like a bulruſh, freſh, green
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:111281:11"/> ſmooth outſide without a knot, but within nothing but a ſpongeous Vaine pith: no wonder if we ſtill fare no better, while ſtill we keepe ſuch unbroken, ſlinty hearts; I remember <hi>Demetrius,</hi> and the reſt <note place="margin">Acts 1934.</note> of his crafty fellowes, cry out two whole houres great, great, is <hi>Diana;</hi> What was <hi>Diana?</hi> an Idoll: what is an Idoll? nothing, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 4. Now what a ſtir had theſe men made two houres about a great, great, nothing; <hi>magnum nihil,</hi> if wee have all this twelve moneth ſowen the wind, we can expect no more but to reape the whirlewind; if all this with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out broken hearts, God may give us that ſad anſwer, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. 23. Ten righteous perſons would ſave <hi>Sodom,</hi> but they muſt be broken hearted ones, alſo in Gods account are no men, <hi>Ier.</hi> 5. 1. But your occaſions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine me onely to ſalute the firſt, that I may larglier ſettle on the ſecond and maine point from the 17. <hi>Verſe,</hi> which is this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſ.</hi> 2. A broken heart &amp; contrite ſpirit is exceeding pleaſing and acceptable to God; ſo the Text its Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices its Sacrifices of God, its ſuch Sacrifices as he will never deſpiſe: ſuch a frame of ſpirit God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mauds, <hi>Ier.</hi> 4. 3. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 10. 12. Such he commends by cleere Texts, <hi>Pſal</hi> 34. 18. &amp; 147. 3. God hath two chiefe places of reſidence, the higheſt Heavens and the loweſt heart, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57. 15. At the proud, God who is higher then the higheſt, ſcornes to looke at them, but hath an Eagles Eye to a broken ſpirit, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56. 2. To helpe ſuch was Chriſt anointed, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61. 1. Such are bleſſed, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 3. By parables; broken hearted Prodigall, <hi>Luk.</hi> 15. The broken hearted Publican, <hi>Eu.</hi> 18. By example; broken hearted <hi>Hannah,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. 1.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:111281:12"/> 
               <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 22. 19, 20, 21. <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 33. 11, 12, 13. &amp;c. A broken veſſell (as St. <hi>Bernard</hi> well) holds Gods liquor the beſt: And now you that are the ſtronger flock of Chriſt, and could journey faſter. afford us a little patience while I unroll the ſtone for your Lambs, and great with young, to drinke a <note place="margin">Acts 19. 34.</note> little, (for why ſhould not we ſpend our braines and lungs, for the pooreſt of theſe, for whom Chriſt died) and then I'le coaſt the ſhore with what good ſpeede I may. Let me a little unfold theſe two things, 1. What is meant by heart, and ſpirit? 2. What, by bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and contrite?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. 1.</hi> Whats here meant by heat and ſpirit?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Not that fleſhly heart in mans body, for if that be pricked or broken the party dies preſently; but mans ſoule or inſide; (take me with you thus in ſhort:) man conſiſts of two eſſentiall parts (or in Scripture phraſe, two men, inward man and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man) body and ſoule, inſide and outſide; now the ſoule (or inſide) according to its ſeverall relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or Offices is called by ſeverall names; from its na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is called a ſpirit, from its principall ſeate, the heart; from its enlivening the body, the ſoule; from one maine Office, the conſcience; yet one and the ſame ſoule: as one man is both Father, Maſter, Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band yet the ſame Man: for I take not the ſpirit, for the purer and more ſpirituall part of the ſoule, <hi>viz.</hi> The underſtanding, and the heart for the lower part or affections, as ſome are pleaſed to ſpeak.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. 2.</hi> How mans ſoule is ſaid to be broken and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> This phraſe implies two things. Firſt, that by
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:111281:12"/> nature our hearts are flinty, ſtony, rocky, hard, need breaking, ſuch are we, ſuch are our Children by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>Ezek</hi> 11. 19. Secondly, that our ſoules might be ſoftned, melted, made contrite which conſiſts maine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in five things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, conviction; when by the word outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, and ſpirit inwardly God convinceth the ſoule of its corruption by natures curſed eſtate, ſinfull life; perhaps at firſt chargeth the ſoule with ſome maine principall ſin as here to <hi>David,</hi> ſo with unchaſtity to Woman of <hi>Canaan. Ioh.</hi> 4. 18. With perſecution to <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 9. 4. And afterwards chargeth a whole ſwarme of ſins (of which he never dreamed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe guilty, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 9.) And cries with <hi>Nathan</hi> here, thou art the man; now he ſees his money is but braſſe, he is not ſo good as he dreamed of; before aske him, are you a ſinner? yes, God have mercy upon us, we are all ſinners; why? have you broken the Law or Goſpell? Elſe you have not ſinned: now come to particulars, aske him, have you broken the firſt Commandement? no, I am no Atheiſt: have you broke the ſecond? No, I am no Papiſt: have you broken the third? No, all the Pariſh knowes I am no ſwearer: have you broken the fourth? No; all my Neighbours know I am a good Church-man: have you broken the fifth? no; I am as dutifull a Child as lives; and ſo of the reſt. Come to the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell; doe you believe? yes, and ever have, ever ſince I was borne, elſe pitty I ſhould live; and ſo indeed glories that he hath not ſinned; but now when God ſets the ſpirituall part of the Law, and his ſins in order and danger before his face, now, he holds
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:111281:13"/> up his hands before Gods Bar, and cries guilty, Lord guilty! every word hits a thumpe on his heart, and he cries. Oh! I have been a vile Traitor and Rebell againſt Heaven, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. Strikes him dead. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 9.</p>
            <p>2. Soule afflication; not onely conſcience is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced, but his heart is pricked, vexed, afflicted, <hi>Lev.</hi> 23 27. what law ſaith outwardly, ſpirit of bondage faſtens it cloſe to the heart inwardly, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 15. Pricked, and pierced in heart, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 37 Cries out oh damned! I feare damned, <hi>Acts.</hi> 16. 30. What ſhall I doe? is there no balme in <hi>Gilead?</hi> The ſoule throbs and cries, Oh what a foole was I? What a good God have I angred? what a ſweete Chriſt, abuſed? what a pretious ſoule have I defiled? What feareful danger have I incurr'd? &amp;c.</p>
            <p>3. Soule ſhaming; ſmites upon his thigh, <hi>Ier.</hi> 31. 19. How mad was I to trade and tug in theſe Brick. kills of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and preferre the puddles of <hi>Damaſeus</hi> before ſilver ſtreams of <hi>Iordan,</hi> aſhamed with <hi>Daniel c.</hi> 9, 7. Bluſh with <hi>Ezra. c.</hi> 9. 5. Confounded in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with prodigall, <hi>Lu.</hi> 15. 21. Grieved exceedingly, <hi>Zach.</hi> 12. 10, 11.</p>
            <p>4. Soule hating and leaving ſin, or leaving it with hatred. Many leave and part with their ſins; <hi>Phaltiel</hi> parted with his Wife <hi>Michol</hi> (formerly maried to <hi>David)</hi> when <hi>David</hi> ſent for her, be left her for feare of being killed by <hi>Abner,</hi> but his teares at parting argued he did not loath her, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3. 16. Or as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners in a ſtorme caſt their goods into the ſea for feare; but hate them not, but now he lookes upon his luſts as a very death. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 24. Caſts them away with deteſtation, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30. 22. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 7. 16. Yee loath
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:111281:13"/> themſelves for them, <hi>Ezech.</hi> 20. 43. yea, part with them. <hi>non cum animo revertendi, Hoſ. 14. 8. 2 Cor. 7. 11.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>5 Soule humility. A lowlineſſe in his owne eyes; ſhall ever I be proud, and puft up, that have had ſuch a heart, ſuch treachery againſt the King of Heaven? when ever proud fleſh ariſeth, his owne vileneſſe keeps him low, downe proud heart; what thou proud, that haſt done thus, and thus againſt thy good God? <hi>Job 7. 20. &amp; 42. 5, 6. Gen. 18. 27.</hi> thus that <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oheſter</hi> Saint, and Martyr, <hi>Bradford,</hi> cloſeth up his ſweet Letters, <hi>miſerrimus peccator,</hi> a very hypocrite, <hi>Iohn Bradford;</hi> thus Saint <hi>Bernard, quaſi quoddam mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruminter filios hominum Sto.</hi> Thus Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> leſſe then the leaſt of Saints; the <hi>Centurion,</hi> unworthy to come under thy roofe; <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> unworthie to untie the latchet of his ſhoes; thus Prodigall, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy to be called thy ſervant, &amp;c. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57. 15.</p>
            <p>This ſhort inch of time enforceth me to paſſe by the reaſons; which I had gleaned, to aſſert this truth; hoping at this time you will take God on his bare word; and ſo I with what haſte I can, poſt to the Uſes, which are like to <hi>Moſes</hi> Arke, from within, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore which let me now draw out to you, 1 <hi>Aarons</hi> Rod of reproofe: 2. The Pot of Manna: 3. The two Tables. And firſt of the laſt, the Tables of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> 1. Theſe Tables plainly ſhew us what a heart every of us hath by nature, <hi>viz.</hi> hard, ſtony, flinty, needs melting, grinding, hewing, unſenſible, inflexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, compared to a ſtone, that drops melt not; to a dead man whom words move not? <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 1. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 11. 19. Aske your ſervant or child when you come
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:111281:14"/> from Church, where was the Text? what was the Sermon? they ſcratch, but not a word; you would wonder how they could ſo quite forget it, or how thoſe flocks of divels that follow the hearer (as birds the ſower) have ſtollen all, <hi>Luke</hi> 8. 5. Let this Servant goe to Market, aske him how this or that graine or goods ſold? what newes? aske him of ſome play or ſhew, he tels you a very ready tale; oh the flinty mind to ſaving truths!</p>
            <p>Offer a man 1000 pound a yeere, to this or that convenient thing; threaten him with great fines, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonments, death; oh, he ſtrats, runs, ſhrinkes, &amp;c. tell him of eternall glory in Heaven, beſides a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dredfold gaine here, or of eternall garboiles and flames in Hell, beſides a hundredfold loſſe here; all theſe never ſtartle, never move him; oh the rockie heart to ſaving good! ſuch are you, ſuch thine by nature, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>2. This Table would have directed us in trying of our ſelves, whether we were ever broken hearted or not; and in this Table I had thought to have men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned foure ſearching ſignes and trials; but having much before me, I muſt be faine at preſent to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. I come next then to the pot of Manna, and it will helpe us the way, how a ſinfull people; with whom God is angry, and hath a terrible controverſie, may yet come to be at peace, and at one with their God againe, how to recover a fainting dying Nation; truely its not Sacrifices, Offerings, but a broken heart that will helpe us, this hath <hi>proba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um eſt</hi> upon it, <hi>de facto</hi> is hath done it. Ionah 3. 6, 7, 8. <hi>Ierem.</hi> 18. 7, 8.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:111281:14"/> this hath the promiſe for it, 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 7. 14. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 18. 30, 31. <hi>Ioel</hi> 2. 13, 14. 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 34. 37. and wonder not, for 1. renting of the heart will heale the rents of a Kingdome; the more hearts are rended the more will the land and its diviſions be glued and cemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>Ioel</hi> 2. 13, 14. Againe, where the hearts are ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for ſinne, there Gods heart is rended with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion to ſuch ſinners, <hi>Ier.</hi> 31. 18, 20. <hi>Hoſea</hi> 11. 8.</p>
            <p>3. God will break us inwardly or outwardly; if not inwardly, then looke for outward breakings, (for broken we muſt be) as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> when his heart would not break, then he was broke in pieces, and his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome alſo; but if heartbroke, then God hath his end, which is not our affliction or deſtruction, but heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breaking, Ezek. 18. 32. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57. 15, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>4. When hearts are broken, then ſins are pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned (as here <hi>Nathan</hi> told <hi>David, 2 Sam.</hi> 12.) and when ſin is pardoned, controverſie is removed, ſo as though God may chaſten in mercy, yet not puniſh in wrath, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1 16, 18, 19.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> But what meanes may I uſe to get my heart broken and contrite (for I no way trouble you with the Schoole diſtinctions of attrite and contrite, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Goe to the great heart-maker, heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mender, heart-ſearcher, by fervent prayer, as <hi>David</hi> here did, <hi>verſ.</hi> 10. God claimes as well heart-mending and curing the ſpirituall ſtone, as a priviledge to himſelfe, <hi>Ezech.</hi> 11. 19. as well as heart ſearching, <hi>Ier.</hi> 17. 10. not withſtanding, uſe the means we muſt: as,</p>
            <p>2. Uſe the hammer of the Law of God, <hi>Ier.</hi> 23. 29. when the Philoſopher jeered <hi>Anthony</hi> the hermite for want of bookes, he told him, Oh Philoſopher, I have
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:111281:15"/> three great bookes, Heaven, Earth, and Sea, and in each of theſe variety of letters, Stars in the booke of Heaven; Men, Beaſts, and Plants in the ſecond book; and Fiſhes in the third; yet none of theſe ſo proper to breake the heart, as this of the word; glaſſe thy ſelfe in this Word, this Low, and it will diſcover to thee foure things to breake thy heart: Firſt, the defiled, woefull, curſed eſtate by nature at firſt; as <hi>David</hi> here <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. 5. as <hi>Paul</hi> tels <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 12, 15. we hate toades for their curſed natures (and ſo ſerpents likewiſe) though they hurt us not; now this great Sea of our miſery, runs (as divines ſpeake) eſpecially into ſix branches: 1. We loſt all our grace, and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall image of God (for the naturall image we could not) whereby we were holy and rightequs (in cur model) like God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 7. &amp; 6. 5.</p>
            <p>2. All mankind, every part of man is defiled with <note place="margin">Adam was the Root, we the Branches, he falling, we all fell; he Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, we ſtreames, he poyſoned, we are all infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted; he Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, we Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, he being a traytor, all out ſtate is conſiſcate by all Law of Nature and Nations.</note> the rootes and ſeeds of all manner of corruption, and made prone to all that is naught, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 52. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. &amp; 1. 29.</p>
            <p>3. In that eſtate our perſons are ſlaves, in bondage to Satan, and to his maſter, (ſinne;) bound already, hand and foote, and indarkneſſe; onely wont tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling into the pit, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. <hi>Eploſ.</hi> 2. 3. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 26. and ſo bound as all world cannot free us, but Ieſus Chirſt <hi>Iohn</hi> 8. 35.</p>
            <p>4. During this eſtate we are quite diſabled from doing God any acceptable ſervice <hi>Prov.</hi> 15. 8. 9. <hi>Iohn</hi> 9. 31. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>5. Have in that eſtate no true ſaving (but onely a common, civill,) right to the Creatures, and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things, <hi>Til.</hi> 1. 15 <hi>(Rom:</hi> 8. 20, 21.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:111281:15"/>
            <p>6. Lyable to all miſery, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59. 1, 2, 3. <hi>Ierem.</hi> 5. 25. <hi>Math.</hi> 25 41.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the Law ſhewes alſo the actuall ſinnes of thy life: As 1. thy vile thoughts, deſires, wiſhes, in thy heart (whether outwardly expreſſed or not, and theſe are all known to God now, and ſhall all be revealed hereafter, <hi>Iob</hi> 42. 2. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 5. and theſe thoughts (which are as thicke in a wicked heart as moats in the Sunne) are ſins in Gods eyes, <hi>Prov.</hi> 24. 9. the thought of foſly is ſin, yea and great ſins, <hi>Acts</hi> 8. 22. pray to God if perhaps the thought of thy heart can be forgiven.</p>
            <p>So 2. Wicked and idle words, and of the leaſt of theſe we muſt give account to God, <hi>Matth.</hi> 12. 36, 37. beſides lying, ſwearing, curſing, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>So 3. Of thy life, againſt the firſt and ſecond Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, towards God and man, againſt every Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, that (as the ancients ſpeake) in the Goſpel, ſome were dead, but not carried forth, as <hi>Iairus</hi> daughter; ſome dead. and carrying forth, but not buried, as Widdows ſonne; ſome dead, carried forth, and buried, as <hi>Lazarus;</hi> ſuch are our ſinnes, ſome dead thoughts in heart, not carried forth; ſome dead words, carried forth by the tongue, but not buried; ſome dead actions, carried forth and buried in the life: and thus we ſinne, by neglecting good, committing evill, and dead performance of what is good.</p>
            <p>3 The law ſhewes us alſo that we are guilty of the ſins of many others, ſome whereof may happily be already in hell for them, ſome perhaps already har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened, others in danger; its a fearefull thing to be
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:111281:16"/> guilty of one <hi>Vriah's</hi> blood; one <hi>Abel's</hi> blood cries lowd; Oh what is it to be guilty of ſo much ſoule blood? of wife, children, ſervants, friends, compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, kindred, neighbours, by perſwading, humoring, inticing, not hindering (where thou haſt a calling and power ſo to do) or any other way furthering their ſin? <hi>(peccatum qui non prohibet cum poſſit jubet)</hi> the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient fathers ſome of them uſed to pray <hi>Domine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte nobis aliena noſtra peccata,</hi> our other mens ſins; the <hi>Rabbins</hi> have a note from <hi>Gen.</hi> 4. 10. the voyce of thy Brothers bloods, that becauſe the word is <hi>[bloods]</hi> in the plurall number in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> (as you ſee in your Margent) therefore its meant, that <hi>Caine</hi> not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly killed <hi>Abels</hi> perſon, but all thoſe that might have come from <hi>Abels</hi> loynes, (had he beene married) and from their proſterity ſucceſſively to the worlds end; ſo thou by thy ſins infecteſt thy children, ſervants; they have families, and many children; and teach theirs accordingly; thy ſin may ſpread to many thouſand perſons ere day of Judgement; how is <hi>Ieroboam</hi> branded, with this brand? <hi>Ieroboam</hi> that made <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſin; Oh what is it to deſtroy a ſoule? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 11.</p>
            <p>4 Law ſhewes our danger in this curſed eſtate; If any of theſe three things happen to us which I ſhall now name; (and any of them or all of them or all of them may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny houre) wee are utterly undone for ever; <hi>viz.</hi> If 1. In this eſtate God ſuffer us to ſin that unpardonable ſin againſt Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Matth. 12. 31, 32. 1 Iohn 5. 16.</hi> Or 2. that God ſweare againſt us in his wrath, and give us up to our owne hearts luſts, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 81. 12. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 12. 40. If God ſay let never grace grow on thee while world laſteth, as <hi>Mark.</hi> 11. 14. Or 3. If
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:111281:16"/> death (any one way of a thouſand; <hi>quolibet momen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mille moriendi modi,)</hi> come and ſeize on thee, thou art eternally undone, thou haſt ſupped ſure; Farewel God, Heaven, hope, for ever: and for want of hope thy heart may breake; Let this danger worke upon thee, <hi>(ex hoc momento pendet aeternitas.)</hi> Thus the Law will be a means to break our hard hearts.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, A third means is melting Goſpel; the conſideration what Chriſt hath done and ſuffered for thee ſo vile a wretch, tendred to thee ſo unworthy a worme; this Feather bed breakes ſome flints more then hammer of Law, thus did it to the prodigall, <hi>Luk.</hi> 15. I remember a Story in our Chronicles (the place I cannot cite, not having bookes) of a poore Cobler that ſometimes lived in <hi>London,</hi> neere a very rich honeſt Merchant, the Merchant was ſo excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding kind to the Cobler, that he wanted neither money, gold, cloths, meate, any thing, but the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant helped him; told him that he ſhould never want any thing which he had; ere long, dayes of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution for the Goſpel came on, and who was the main man to accuſe and perſecute the rich Merchant &amp; endanger both his life and fortune, but this Cobler? yet ſo it pleaſed God the Merchant eſcaped; after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Cobler would never meet the Merchant, but ran to the other ſide of ſtreet, or turnd back whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he came neere him; but in a ſtrait lane one day the Merchant purpoſely met him; and ſayes, I freely for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give thee all the wrong you have done me, I will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thinke worſe of thee, come to me at any time, and I will afford thee any help or meanes I can; at which kindneſſe the Cobler falls downe, almoſt bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:111281:17"/> againe in his owne teares, was ſo overcome with this free mercy; that it broke and melted him into as loving and dutifull a poore Neighbour as li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved: Oh! Jeſus Chriſt hath laid downe his life for us wretches! Tendred to us Goſpell, Heaven, &amp;c. Yet we by our ſinnes ſhew this Chriſt, brought upon him unſpeakable ſufferings, perſecuted him in his members, proved falſe with him in the covenant, &amp;c. Yet he followes us to our doores &amp; conſciences with free mercy, promiſing both to forgive, <hi>Exodus</hi> 34. 7. And to forget what hath beene amiſſe, <hi>Ier.</hi> 31. 34. And <hi>Mica.</hi> 7. 18. And to helpe us for this life, for next, for body, ſoule, grace and glory; Oh let all this kindneſſe melt us, let all this goodneſſe winne us to Repentance, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 4. As <hi>Jer.</hi> 3. 22. When the <hi>Jewes</hi> had fouly fallen and againe back ſliden, and ſtill God calls and runs after them with mercy,
<q>Oh this melts them and they cry out, Oh Lord! be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold we come to thee for thou art the Lord our God.</q> Such a melting glory <hi>Ruffin,</hi> tells of Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> the Evangeliſt towards a yong man fallen away, but I haſten, &amp;c. Goates Milke breakes this Ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, meanes to breake our hearts, is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of Gods Workes, even theſe may helpe us this way, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 33. 12. <hi>Pſalme</hi> 119. 71. <hi>Luke</hi> 15. 16, 17. And becauſe this is <hi>Verbum diei</hi> moſt ſuitable to the preſent times, lend me ſomuch patience as a little to enlarge it in ſome particular conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons relating to our owne caſe, and here conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, 1. What great mercies <hi>England</hi> hath had; mercies poſitive, great peace, great plenty, great
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:111281:17"/> ſtore of Goſpell; comparative mercies (give mee leave ſo to ſpeake) great peace, Goſpel, and plenty, then any other Nation in the World, ſince the firſt light darted from above: Before the fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> he had never that great mercy of Chriſt to dye, &amp;c. (having no ſinne, needed no Saviour,) he had a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of workes, we of grace, he (as the Angels now) juſtified by inherent righteouſneſſe, (though then no merit) we by the Righteouſneſſe of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther impured; 2. From the fall of <hi>Adam</hi> till Chriſt the Church was in its ſwadling cloths, under darke types and ſhadowes, <hi>Moſes's padagogie;</hi> but now the Vaile is rent, Types fulfilled, Chriſt is come, and all things cleared, 3. After Chriſt, during Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive times, what raging ten Perſecutions, many hundred Chriſtians ſluine every day in the yeare, ſave the firſt day of <hi>Ianuary?</hi> And what helliſh here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies did the Dragon belch up? Eſpecially foure, that occaſioned foure generall Councells; 4. Since then how hath God cleared up the Goſpell in theſe parts? and for peace; admirable! Its thought wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy the Regiſtring in Scripture, that twice, the <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wes</hi> had peace and reſt forty yeares, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 3. 11. &amp; 5. 31. But once for a wonder its Chronicled that Gods Church had peace eighty yeares together, <hi>Iudg</hi> 3. 30 But we beyond them, above eighty yeares peace; our fore-fathers would have given whole Cart-leads of Hay and Corne in King <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth his time, for a few Chapters of St. <hi>Matthews</hi> Goſpel, or St. <hi>Iames's</hi> Epiſtle; yea Bibles in Engliſh not permitted; yea latter; in the beginning of that Virgin Queene <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Raigne; we have heard,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:111281:18"/> ſuch a man was one of the third or fourth Preachers in the ſhire, now more good Sermons in one City in a moneth, then was in all <hi>England</hi> in a yeare; and for plenty, admired by our friends, envied by our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, tell me of any Nation in all points the like, <hi>Et eris mihi magnus Apollo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay let me adde, ſuperlative mercies, above all mens expectation, who would have ſaid, <hi>Gen.</hi> 21. 7. That <hi>Sarah</hi> ſhould give ſuck; ſo who would have ſaid three yeares agoe, that we ſhould have a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, a trienniall Parliament, and that not to be broken up without mutual conſent? &amp;c. Who would have ſaid ſuch great things ſhould be done or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured thereby? Nay mercies above the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary courſe of Gods providence and dealing with others, a promiſe in the Bible; we have ſuch na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall ſinnes for which God plagued and threatned other Nations, yet we exempted by ſpeciall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative (as a godly Divine ſaid well.) Nay mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies above all the plots of devill and devilliſh men; have wee not had formerly and lately, againſt us <hi>French</hi> plots, <hi>Spaniſh</hi> plots, <hi>Iriſh</hi> plots, <hi>Engliſh</hi> plots; and a plot, a plot, a plot, and ſtill a plot, yet God hath ſoared us above all, as on Eagles wings.</p>
            <p>Adde to theſe alſo, privative mercies; hath not God delivered us from heatheniſme when this poore Iland worſhipped every ſeverall day a ſeverall God; the <hi>Moone</hi> on Munday, <hi>Tuiſco</hi> on Tueſday, &amp;c. But God delivered us: after this, came <hi>Egyptian</hi> dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Popery, but God gave the beaſt a blow in King <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth his time; brought him on all foure in King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth time; gave him a
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:111281:18"/> deadly blow, in famous Queene, <hi>Elizabeths</hi> dayes, and ſtill more and more doth (and I hope will) his head and hornes and heart periſh; did not God miraculouſly deliver us both in fire (that helliſh pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derplot, the devills maſter-peece) and in water (in 88.) <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43. 2. Did he not doe as much three yeares agoe when two <hi>Iſraclites</hi> were contending to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, two ſiſter Nations? but I might in theſe be infinite, if I looked on theſe two yeares laſt paſt; years (not as formerly of mercies, but) of miracles. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conſider.</p>
            <p>2. Gods warnings to <hi>England,</hi> warned us by the Miniſtery as to <hi>Ninoveh, Ionah</hi> 3. 4. Warned us by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, all the World (almoſt) on fire round about us; nay warned us by viſible wonders; how did God warn <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> ere its deſtruction; and <hi>Germany</hi> ere its troubles, with many marvelous ſignes and prodigies (as you ſee of late in <hi>print)</hi> and hath he not done as much for us (and all theſe ſignes have voyces to warne us, <hi>Exodus</hi> 4. 8.) Was not that booke, called the preparation to the Croſſe, taken out of a fiſhes maw at the Commencement time in <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> (when many Miniſters and others from all parts were met together, a faire warning, for <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to prepare for the Croſſe? what ſpoke thoſe extraordinary redoubled tides? Strong birth at Stone-houſe neer <hi>Plymouth;</hi> the exceeding ſtrange thunders and lightning at <hi>Withcombe</hi> in <hi>Devon, Octobr.</hi> 21. 1638. At <hi>Anthony</hi> in <hi>Cornwall</hi> on Whitſunday, 1640. The ſeverall ſtories are in print, ſo at <hi>Chid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lington</hi> in <hi>Hartfordſhire;</hi> at <hi>Wakefield</hi> in <hi>Yorkeſhire,</hi> and many other warnings from Earth, Sea, Heaven, all, &amp;c. Such as, <hi>Amos</hi> 4. 6, 7, 9. 10, 11, &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:111281:19"/>
            <p>3. Conſider bleeding <hi>Ireland,</hi> let that breake our hearts, how many Husbands, Wives, Childrens Throats, how many houſes, Families, have our ſinnes, there cut, ruined, deſtroyed? I have heard of one that eſpying a Woman that cut his Wife and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens Throats, he was in ſuch exreme paſſion and rage that hee was ſtruck dumbe; and no wonder; Oh thinke what wee have done; if one from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Sea ſend any Armour, or Amunition, to ruine the loyall ſubjects and ſtrength of <hi>England,</hi> Oh how vexed and angry are we! Alas wee have ſent over our ſinnes, the worſt Armour and Amunition againſt poore <hi>Ireland,</hi> &amp;c. But the glaſſe is my ſaithfull monitor.</p>
            <p>4. Conſider <hi>Englands</hi> grievous ſinnes, let them <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudg. 5. 8.</hi> Never was mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery on the <hi>Iewes,</hi> but ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry was one or the onely Cauſe; or as the <hi>Iewes</hi> ſpake in every cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity there was ſomething of the golden Calfe.</note> melt us; (and now I am in a Sea) I will onely heave up a drop or two.) 1. Grievous Idolatry; a dividing ſinne, what cauſed God to divide the Kingdome of <hi>Iſrail</hi> into two Kindomes twixt <hi>Solomon</hi> his Sonne and ſervant, but becauſe <hi>Solomon</hi> divided Gods worſhip twixt God and idolls? See 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 11. 6. 7, 8. 11. Oh that we ſhould ſuffer thoſe <hi>Cananites</hi> and <hi>Perizzites,</hi> of whom God hath ſo by fire and water warned us, ſtill to be pricks in our ſides, and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be ſnares to us <hi>Iudge</hi> 2. 3. 2 Our great a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe, of long peace, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 3. 30. Of great plenty, we waxed fat and kicked, (as <hi>Iſrael)</hi> of great Goſpell; <hi>Rogers</hi> the firſt Martyr in Queene <hi>Maries</hi> dayes told <hi>Iohn Day</hi> (fellow Priſoner with him, and he that afterwards did print the Booke of Martyrs) three ſtrange things, 1. Brother <hi>Day</hi> I ſhall burne at a Stake, and you be delivered, 2. Thou ſhalt live to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:111281:19"/> ſee the Lady <hi>Elizabeth</hi> (now in Priſon,) to be Queen of <hi>England,</hi> (both theſe proved true) and, 3. Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (ſaid he) then tell my brethren in <hi>England,</hi> unleſſe they uſe the Goſpell better then we have done, there lies a heavier ſtorme of vengeance over their heads then ever hung over ours; they had ſix yeares Goſpell in King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixrs dayes and (as he ſaid) abuſed it (ſo complained the exiles in <hi>Frank ford</hi> of that ſinne) and God ſent them five yeares fiery tribulation in <hi>Queene Maries</hi> dayes; we have had ſince eighty foure years of much more light of the Goſpell, Oh—but I haſten to a third great ſinne, <hi>viz.</hi> Contempt and abuſe of Gods faithfull Miniſters and people, is it not as in <hi>Eliſha's</hi> dayes, that Men, Women, yea little Children, cry, come up thou Round-head, come up thou Round-head (I ſhould have ſaid,) thou bald-Head, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 23. But take heed ſome ſhe Beares, or viſible marks of Gods Anger ſeiſe not on thee and thine, as <hi>verſe</hi> 24. So abuſe of Gods Miniſters, 2 <hi>Chronicles</hi> 36. 16. Chriſts Members, Jewells, Apple of his Eye, &amp;c. Adde, 4. Gur Sabbath breaking, and that with <note place="margin">Sabbath break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was a ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of <hi>Germany</hi> (as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mſelves confeſſe) and ſure things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver went well in <hi>England</hi> ſince Sabbath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breaking was tolerated and allowed.</note> authority, as 2 <hi>Chronicles</hi> 36. 11. So, 5. Not laying to heart the afflictions of <hi>Ioſeph, Amos</hi> 6. 6. And ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more; all theſe (this banning, damning, curſing, ſwearing, whoredome, with which I am loath to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>file the Ayre and abuſe your patience) ſhould break our hearts.</p>
            <p>5 Conſider alſo <hi>Englands</hi> grievous rents and divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, to helpe to rend our hearts, behold not onely a man of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and an <hi>Egyptian,</hi> but <hi>Iſraelites</hi> coaten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding together; of all Gods judgements Warre ſeems
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:111281:20"/> the worſt and ſoreſt, witneſſe <hi>Davids</hi> choyce, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24. 13, 14. therefore its uſually mentioned the firſt in the ranke, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 6. 11. <hi>Jerem.</hi> 44. 12, 13. where Famine and Peſtilence are, they oftentimes hold out the ſword; but where the ſword goes, uſually it brings in both the other with it; but of all warre, my Leta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny is, from Civill Warre among our ſelves, good Lord deliver us: as being of all other 1. moſt unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, nothing got by fighting among our ſelves. 2. Moſt unchriſtian, for men profeſſing the ſame Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, to quarrell. 3. The moſt unnaturall, father on one ſide, Sonne on the other ſide; Father againſt Sonne, Sonne againſt Father; Brother againſt Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. 4. Moſt dangerous, while we contend toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, all of us lye open to a common enemy, (never was any conqueſt of this Land, but this way) 5. Moſt hurtfull to others, while we contend, wee make our ſelves unhelpfull to bleeding <hi>Ireland</hi> and other Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. 6. Moſt ſcandalous, what will the heathen, what will our enemies ſay? <hi>Cornelius de lapide</hi> may change his note on <hi>Iſai.</hi> 11. Alas are not we a houſe divided, and a Kingdome divided againſt our ſelves? If we bite and devoure one another, ſhall wee not be devoured one of another? <hi>Luk.</hi> 11. 17. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5 15. When God was wont to plague his worſt enemies, it was with ſending the ſpirit of diviſion one againſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, and ſo one ruining another, <hi>Judg.</hi> 7. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20. <hi>Midianites, Moabites, Ammonites; &amp;c.</hi> Nay, 2. conſider what great things lye now at ſtake, not our Eſtates onely, but Liberties, nay lives, (how many a gallant man already ſlaine? and many more in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,) my his ſacred Majeſties perſon is in danger,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:111281:20"/> the breath of our noſtrills, &amp;c. <hi>Lam.</hi> 4. 20. A certain man may draw a bow at a venture, and as ſoone hit the <hi>King,</hi> as another man, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 22. 34. Nay dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger hence to all the Proteſtant Churches under Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, nay Religion, the Goſpell it ſelfe, the Goſpell, that pretious <hi>Goſpel,</hi> in danger to be removed (though all world cannot ruine it) In the riſing in the <hi>North</hi> in Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> dayes, the popiſh army came out of the <hi>North</hi> to <hi>Durham, Darnton, Tadcaſter, &amp;c.</hi> And as they came, burnt Bibles; look at <hi>Shilo,</hi> at 7. churches of <hi>Aſia, Ieruſalem, Egypt, Rome,</hi> &amp;c. &amp; let this break our hearts.</p>
            <p>6 Conſider againe, this may break our hearts, that by our ſins we ſhould ſtop God (as I may ſay) when he was ſo gloriouſly going on, in ſuch a bleſſed work of reformation; In the beginning of this Parliament how did the beautifull <hi>Zerah</hi> of mercy and reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Gen.</hi> 38. 28, 29, 30. Breake out with a pretious hand, full of bleſſings? but how have our ſinnes brought forth the ſtormy <hi>Pharez</hi> of troubles firſt? ſo in King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth his dayes, there were as faire beginnings of reformation (all things conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) as ever; but how did ſin ſtay the children when come to the birth; and that glorious Sun ſet under a cloud? So in King of <hi>Swedens</hi> time, what mighty hopes? yet ere long extremly nipt by our ſins; ſo ſtill; and who can yet ſay that the bitternes of death is paſt? how have miſeries growne on us of late? from differences in mind to paper and quill-conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, from that to raiſing forces, from that to blowes, to bloud? and from hence <hi>God</hi> knowes whither; our ſins may cauſe <hi>God</hi> to hiſſe for the flye beyond the River, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 7. 18. (but of this more then enough) oh let this break our ſpirits!</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:111281:21"/>
            <p>7. Conſider that if our hearts and Spirits were kindly broken, who knowes what a day may yet bring forth? its eaſie with our great and good God to bring all things about, as in <hi>Ahaſhuerus</hi> and <hi>Eſthers</hi> daies; as <hi>Iſaac</hi> from the Mount, <hi>Peter</hi> from priſon in the very nicke of time, when almoſt quite gone; <hi>Daniel.</hi> and the three children, when paſt the helpe of man; yea, God loves to doe thus, that himſelfe may alone have the glory, as in <hi>Gideons</hi> caſe, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 7. 2, &amp;c. One of the three moſt glorious viſions in the old Teſtament, (as the Rabbyes ſpeake) was, that <hi>Exod.</hi> 3. 23. where God ſhewed upon Mount <hi>Horeb</hi> or <hi>Sinai,</hi> to <hi>Moſes</hi> (now 80. yeeres old) a buſh, NO tall <hi>Cedar,</hi> or high Tree, but a low buſh,) this buſh ſignified the low condition of the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in <hi>Egypt:</hi> the fire in the buſh noted the fiery tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and perſecutions they there endured under <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rooh;</hi> yet becauſe Chriſt (the Angell of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant) was there, therefore all <hi>Egypt</hi> could not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume that poore buſh, nay that fire was a meanes to haſten them the faſter to the promiſed Land. Though we are gone beyond mans, yet not beyond Gods helpe; who knowes but God may now and hereby be working ſome great and glorious mercy for his Church? if we had hearts fit for the mercy, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20. 33. even broken ſpirits; ſure we are that Antichriſt muſt downe: in Gods Decree and the Churches faith he is downe, as good as downe, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, <hi>Revel</hi> 18. 2. no wonder, he hath the curſe of God, the ſinnes of thouſands lying heavie on him; thouſands of thundering prayers againſt him, and not one prayer in all the world for him; for all wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedmen,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:111281:21"/> ſweare they can, curſe, banne, drinke, (dam me) they can, but pray they cannot, not truly, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66. 8. <hi>Iſa</hi> 66. 3. now he that is ſo without God, prayer, promiſe, hope, &amp;c. how can he ſtand? what is able to ſtand againſt the great Cannons of Gods. peoples prayers? I am not a Prophet, nor ſonne of a Prophet, I confeſſe I know not the times and the ſeaſons, onely give me leave to tell you the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of others, both of our owne and tranſmarine Divines, and I ſhall leave you to your owne opinions herein. M. <hi>Brightman</hi> (a man whom his worſt ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies cannot juſtly accuſe either of impiety or igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, a man ſurely pious and learned) in his notes on <hi>Canticle</hi> 6. and on <hi>Revel.</hi> 19, 4. ſaith, that the firſt calling of the Iewes (that reſurrection as it were from the dead, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. 15.) ſhall be about the yeere 1650. Now before the ſixt Angell poure his Viall upon the River <hi>Euphrates</hi> that thoſe Kings of the Eaſt, the Iewes, may come in <hi>Revel.</hi> 16. 12. the fiſt Angell muſt firſt poure his Vial, upon the ſeate of the beaſt, <hi>Revel.</hi> 16. 10, 11. Antichriſt muſt firſt goe downe; to him accords a great Divine of our owne, and brings many Scriptures to prove it; (as you ſee in print) ſo have many of late both of our own, and forren Divines, jumped on the ſame time. 2. Others adde, that three propheticall daies and a halfe, <hi>Revel.</hi> 11. 9. that is) three yeers and a half, muſt Gods faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full witneſſes, his <hi>Zerubbabels</hi> and <hi>Ioſhua's,</hi> the faithfull of God, ſuffer a great perſecution, juſt before Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt goe down; now if this be a truth, then may this great trouble fore-run a great mercy; God ſhewed to <hi>Abraham</hi> a viſion, <hi>Gen.</hi> 15. 17. after a ſmoaky furnace,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:111281:22"/> comes a bright ſhining lamp; I cannot tell whether ſo great a bleſſing be ſo nigh, as within 8 or 10 yeers, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">Sun ſhines ſwee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eſt after a great ſhowre.</note> this I am conſident of, that Antichriſt muſt down, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14. 6, 8. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. 8. that Chriſt wil have a glorious Church, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. 12, 15. that God will cleare his Saints, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60. 13. but of the day and houre, or yeere, here I ſtick. Here are great ſtirs, combuſtions, and buſtlings, in <hi>England, Ireland,</hi> &amp;c. as ever were, and I can ſurely tell you what will be the end of all theſe (though I be no Pophet) this namely will be the end, which is <hi>Iſa.</hi> 3. 10, 11. Let man and divell doe their worſt, the end ſhall be well to the righteous, and wo to the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked. <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 6. 13, 18 26.</note> Oh! let us get and labour for broken hearts, that ſo theſe happy daies may be haſtned: &amp; now I eſpie the ſhore, and its time I ſhould; my time, and your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience both expect it. Thus much therefore for the pot of Manna wherein I have long been ſearching; I cloſe up all with <hi>Aarons</hi> rod; and this rod in the third uſe reproves thoſe that like worſe of their friends, wives, children, ſervants, &amp;c. becauſe they are pricked <note place="margin">Vſe 3.</note> in their hearts, and conſciences, tender and broken; as <hi>Saul</hi> of <hi>Ionathan, Iobs</hi> wife of <hi>Iob, Nabal</hi> of <hi>Abigail, Artaxerxes</hi> of <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> &amp;c. that ſay to them as <hi>Balak</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to <hi>Balaam</hi> (and its moſt helliſh policy) <hi>Numb.</hi> 24. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> thy God hath hindred thee from honour.</p>
            <p>2. Thoſe that thinke their own eſtates nought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have feares, doubts, troubles, griefes, &amp;c. alas we muſt all be Souldiers, and ſhall a Souldier have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o combate, troubles, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem that have no care to keep their hearts ſoft and in a good temper (having ſo many means that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> once God hath in ſome meaſure broke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:111281:22"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> How may we keep our hearts ſoft?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> There are foure things much talked of now adaies, which in the ſence they are ſpoken I much underſtand not, <hi>viz.</hi> Malignant parties. 2. Poſture of defence. 3. Ordering of the Militia. 4. Trayning. But in a ſpirituall ſenſe to keepe thy heart ſoft, take them thus:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Kill, and be daily oppoſing that malignant party, I meane thy luſts (believe it, theſe are the worſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants in the World) as men to keep the Ice from freezing daily potter in it, ſo daily ſearch thy heart for theſe Malignants, and labour their death.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Get thy ſoule into a poſture of defence, into the Rock Chriſt, the onely true defence, and ſafe refuge, run to and claſp more firmely upon him daily.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Order the Militia, get up thy ſpirituall armor, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6. daily more girded to thee, labour to thrive in grace.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Train or exerciſe (but I mean) S. <hi>Pauls</hi> exerciſe daily, <hi>Acts</hi> 24. 16. herein do I exerciſe my ſelfe, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Though thou be overtaken with a ſinne lie not down in it, (that hardned <hi>David</hi> exceedingly, his ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in ſin) eſpecially now, when Armies goe out to battell, <hi>Deut.</hi> 23. 9. when you lie down in ſin you give place to the divell to be your bedfellow, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 26, 27.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Keep Saints company, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 25, 26, 27.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Often ponder the afflictions and diſtreſſes of our brethren, as if we were our ſelves in bonds, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 3. take not that liberty, merriment now, this Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſſe, that otherwiſe lawfully thou migheſt; ſee <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riahs</hi> practice, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11. 11. ſo <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> though in great place, Kings Cup-bearer, <hi>Neh.</hi> 2. 3. If a loving
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:111281:23"/> Wife had a Husband that lay panting at laſt gaſpe, would ſhe feaſt and make merry, and ſay, is it not lawfull? ſure its not then ſit for her to doe ſo; if thy mother lay drawing her laſt breath, thou wouldſt with a ſad heart run for any helpe for her; and ſhould we not for our mother <hi>England?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude all, Seeke out that old leaven, that darling right hand of thy ſoule; let every one ſweep before his own doore, it will make all ſtreets cleaner; and then ſeeke out thy family ſin; and then the ſins of the towne and place thou liveſt in; and laſtly, the <hi>Achans</hi> and Wedges of Gold in the Nation; humble thy ſelfe, mourne for them, purge them out, who can tell but yet we may ſee happy times? however broken hearts will beare and goe through the worſt times with comfort.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But theſe combuſtious and troubles give little hope of happy times.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Things are never worſe to be liked; there was never any great good brought about, but there was firſt great rubs lay in the way. When <hi>Luther</hi> ſet upon a reformation, all the world was againſt <hi>Luther,</hi> and he againſt all the world. When King <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. ſet upon the ſame worke, there were divers commotions and rebellions in <hi>England;</hi> ſo it was ere the Iewes came out of <hi>Egypt;</hi> ere they rebuilt their Temple at <hi>Ieruſalem;</hi> when Chriſt was going about the worke of our redemption, what oppoſition? But leſt I ſhould too long detaine you, and hinder your preſſing buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, I abruptly breake off: The Lord give to you and me broken hearts. Thus much therefore be ſaid of that which we can never doe too much.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:111281:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
